Welcome everybody. Thank you for coming.
I know for
It's probably expensive for everybody,
but it's
I think it's a beautiful city and I
It's one of my favorite cities in the
world. So, I think it's
I I like to have a nice place to teach.
I like I don't care about my house or my
money or things like that, but I I like
a nice place to teach.
Thank you Tim and everyone for arranging
it.
Uh
The Three Jewels was a really really
difficult thing and and we wanted to
start a center in New York.
And um
I remember the day we started looking
for the place.
And it was a very bad winter day and it
was blowing very cold. It was like
December and January.
And
uh in those days the
very difficult to find any place to rent
in New York City. It was very very
crowded and very expensive and
and me and Annie Pema, we walked through
the city.
Uh lower east side? Lower west side?
East side.
And we we walked and walked and walked.
It was so cold and it was so
depressing. We couldn't find anything.
Couldn't find any place to rent in the
Finally, we we reached this place and uh
it was a clothing store before.
Very small and it had three stories.
And
there was a very bad fire.
And it was all burned out and uh
we called the landlord. We said, "We'll
take it."
You know, he's like, "What?"
We said, "We'll take it, you know." And
he's "How much do you want?" He said,
"It's You can't use it. It's worthless,
you know." We said, "We'll fix it.
Uh
you know, and then you give us rent free
for a few months
and we'll fix it. And you remember Andy
Grace? Yeah.
So, we had a
we had a carpenter who worked who was a
student.
And we fixed it. It took us, I don't
know, 6 months.
And we had to tear out all the burnt
wood and the
all the bricks and
then I asked
Lama Pelma,
you know, you will you be the director?
And she took the apartment above the
above the store.
And below the below the store, there was
uh
we call it boiler room. We call boiler
room. It's where the heater is. And it's
the old kind of heater. It's very very
dirty.
Like oil and coal and like that.
And in fact, the city
came and closed it because they said it
also has asbestos problem. You know,
it's cancer. You can
So, we tore out all the asbestos and uh
and we made an office down there. If you
know Punzo,
uh
who still works for Nancy Karen,
he was the
he used to grade everybody's homeworks
down next to the boiler.
And
I used to sneak down there
and sleep under his desk
on the floor
because I couldn't
find any place where people
let me rest. So, that's still true.
So, I hide I hide under the his desk and
I sleep on the floor under his desk.
And
it was nice.
that's how Three Jewels started. And it
was really hard to start it.
Recently, I
uh,
I was in New York and I checked Yelp
for a yoga center and it's it's number
one in New York. In all of New York it's
number one.
It's the number one yoga center in New
York. Yeah. Yeah.
Then I I always wanted to have a
bookstore ever since I was a little kid.
And,
I bought Shakespeare.
I bought the classics, Dante. I put all
these great books in there.
And, I gave her then I I had to go back
to the diamond business.
And I was really busy for like 2 months.
And, I came back
and all the books are gone.
Uh, and I'm like,
"Thelma, where's the books?" She said,
"People stole them."
You know, the homeless people stole
them.
You know, I said, "Well, what Why are
the homeless people in here?" She said,
"I invited all of them to stay here
in the three jewels." It was and they
all sleep on the couch and they sleep
everywhere on the chairs.
Then, uh,
New York people don't even want to come
in.
And, then there's a guy,
uh, veteran?
Like he had one leg or something.
And he got a TV and he put it in the
three jewels and he watched, uh, war
movies all day.
Really loud.
So, I walk in and, uh,
it's all homeless people and, uh,
there's a few outside
on the sidewalk selling the last books.
Uh, on in front of the store.
They're selling the the last of the
books, you know.
And, I'm like, "What are you What are
you doing, you know?"
And she said, "You told me to build a
community center."
And it's a community center. it's just
homeless community center.
And I thought later much later I thought
it was a great thing.
Uh
so
that's that's who she was.
And she was so popular in the
in the East Village. Every homeless
person is like, "Hi everybody."
And very funny, very funny.
Next door you can find all the drugs
really dangerous people
these people are carrying guns, you
know. I'm like, I didn't tell her this.
She's like, "Oh, they're okay."
You know,
and
it was really cool.
All right, she's the only person who did
two three year retreats.
in our home group.
The only one who could do it.
All right, we're going to go back to the
text. You guys ready? Yeday
Bashik.
It's the text Timothy.
Yeah, good. Okay.
Uh the dark letter is the lojong. Lojong
means 1,000 years ago, written 1,000
years ago.
And we're in the middle of lojong.
Lo means mind
and jong means to practice.
Uh
but it also has a pun because it also
means to purify your mind.
So jang or jong
uh means to clean clean something or
make it pure.
And lo means your mind, so it means to
make a habit
of this way of thinking. So today we're
going to describe a way of thinking.
And uh you you hold it on the inside.
And you keep it on the inside. So this
our advice
from 1,000 years ago
uh how to hold a certain state of mind
all day long, okay? And he's going to
talk a lot about losing that state of
mind. How do you
keep it
when the day is long or you're tired or
things are not working well?
How do you keep that? And if you can
keep it, it's called lojong.
Mhm, you did bashak gunded then means uh
yiday means uh
keep keep happy thought, keep peaceful
mind.
Bashak means only that, no other kinds
of thought. Gyun means in a in a stream.
Keep it in a stream all day. See if you
can keep your mind in a happy place all
day, okay? And it's very very difficult.
Uh shepa ni drowa so chuna
pawa dong so namto mambo.
He says uh a lot of us
uh
we think that if we can collect more
money
and if we can collect more
real estate, more houses or things
things like that. If we can collect more
things
money and things. So chuna
pawa, when you get money
and when you get a place
uh pawa dong suma, then you start to
have
extra problems. Pawa means you have to
try to increase your money. Once you get
pretty rich
most people just want to get more rich.
So they they're concentrating
how to multiply their money.
So nam means then when you get pretty
good money
a second problem starts, how to protect
it.
Keep it keep other people from the
money. Protect the money from other
people, okay?
Uh namto is a very nice Tibetan word.
If you spell it with an s r t o g s
it means realization.
And if you take the s off
it means stupid worries all day. Okay,
it's very interesting, okay? And
a lot of people mistranslate it.
Okay, so that's something for you guys,
Rebecca. Namtok without the S
means stupid worries all day.
Like, how can I get more money? How can
I make more money? How can I get more
things?
And lots of people offer me houses.
Lot.
And they offer me big amounts of money
and I'm like, "No, I I'm okay."
I have the smallest legal house in my
town.
And it's on a mountain. We don't even
the road is a dirt road.
And everybody's like, "You don't want to
make a real road?" I'm like, "It is a
real road. It's okay."
And I don't have to
protect the house. Nobody wants it.
You know, so I don't have to worry about
it, you know?
It's just there, you know?
Namtok mambo yee mee day wah mee che he
says, "Don't
Don't spend your whole day worrying
about, you know, your extra house or
your extra money or your extra stock
account or something like that.
If you don't have those things, you
don't have to worry about it. Then you
can think about Dharma
or or taking care of homeless people,
stuff like that.
Yee mee day mee che menong tso eh sum
nyom mempa and you also if you lose your
money, if you didn't care about it in
the first place, you feel relaxed when
you lose it.
And you're like, "Okay, so I lost some
money. It's okay."
By the way, if you can learn to live on
no money,
that's better than having money.
Okay, if you can learn to live without
much money,
then it doesn't matter you have money or
not. And it's a very useful skill.
Um my wife and I both come from poor
families, so we're like
we just relax all the time. We don't
think about it. We don't worry about it.
Uh nyom mempa yee pa daki chen sum la
Uh this is a very very important phrase
in the
Lam Rim
okay Lam Rim next line.
Uh
this is a very important phrase in the
Diamond Way.
People asking me, "Oh, please teach the
Diamond Way. Teach us Vajrayana." Here's
You want some Vajrayana? It's here.
Okay, secret teaching should be put in
the open book.
Uh
and this is very famous. Say Lam Rim.
Lam Rim
Lam means what? You guys know.
Yeah, path.
The Singapore people say path.
And Rim means to carry something. Rim
means to carry something.
Lam Rim means
make it into a path.
Make it into a path. And it means
if you're really good at Lojong,
then good things happen to you.
Like you get a lot of money.
You can use it as a path. You know how
to use it as a path. You can
use it successfully and help many
people.
And then if you don't make any money,
you can also use that as a path. Like
Lojong person is very flexible.
If they have something, they can use it
as a
path.
And if they don't have it, they can use
that as a path.
And this is very important.
In the secret teachings,
this refers to death. Okay, how to use
death
as a path to go higher. Okay, and it's
very beautiful.
Okay, you learn each stage of
death process.
You learn what's going to go in your
mind,
and you learn to take this terrible
experience and use it as a path, right
to them.
Path use it as a path to the higher to
higher goals, okay? So, this expression
uh
it's very beautiful and and by the way,
Lamrim
what we're going through now
it includes secret
teachings. Okay, it the end of the
Lamrim is Vajrayana.
So, it's allowed
if you if you study the this book
at the end of the book, you can study
secret teachings, okay? I think he's
going he's kind of starting to go there,
okay?
Lam to care. Here it says you if you
lose your money
or you lose your job or something like
that,
then
Lojong means automatically think, "Hmm,
how can I use this?
How can I use this to do something
good?" Okay, that's Lam to care. How can
I use this? That attitude is
is Lam to care. And for a real Buddhist,
uh it's a beautiful beautiful ability.
And you have to try to develop it, okay?
Anything happens to you,
good thing, you don't go crazy.
And then any terrible thing happened to
you, you don't go crazy. You say, "Oh,
hmm, how can I use this? How can I use
this for
my to develop myself?"
Uh
and in the secret
teachings,
uh
if you want to practice some secret
Buddhism,
uh you have to think the Buddha sent
this to you.
Okay, the Buddha sent you a good stock.
Stock market went up in your stock.
And suddenly you got rich. And and then
you say, "Oh, Buddha sent me money
today.
How can I use that? What am I supposed
to do? What's a Buddha Why did Buddha
send me money today?
What am I supposed to use this money
for? Okay, that's called
good side, right? Then bad side, if you
you start
disaster,
and you lose all your money. My
grandmother left me
blue chip stock.
Uh my family is a Chevrolet family. My
family family family family help found
Chevrolet company. She When she died,
she left us uh
we call blue chip stock. It's the best
of the best of the best of the
It's a GM GMC. It's in uh
I think the next year it went bankrupt.
But for the first time in a hundred
years or something, it just suddenly,
you know, I took the paper to the stock
broker,
and he said, "Uh you can use it for
toilet paper or something.
You know, otherwise, you just throw it
away. It's It's no You can't use it for
anything."
So,
in this tradition, lojong,
you think uh Buddha sent you a present.
Buddha
made stock market disaster today.
Or Buddha made the stock market spike go
up suddenly.
And then you try to
figure out what's the message. What's
the message, you know? Buddha's sending
me a message. Mhm.
Maybe I'm supposed to help ACI.
You know, maybe I'm supposed to save Tim
salary problem with all his staff.
You know, or like that. You have to Or
you lose all your money. And then you
have to think, "Why did Buddha
Why did Buddha make me lose all my
money?" And then everything is like
that, okay? A real real lojong person
is paranoid.
They're like
everywhere there's Buddha.
You know, trying to tell you something
and and I meet people like that and and
my friends say, "Oh,
this lady is coo-coo, you know? Don't
talk to her."
I'm like, "No, maybe that's a best one,
you know?"
They say, "Buddha sent me a message." I
say, "Yeah, what's the message?"
And it's good. It's healthy healthy
crazy.
Okay, we call it lojong.
Everything has a purpose.
Everything After you sit in this class
today,
you have to be good
crazy. Good crazy.
Good crazy means everything is a message
from Buddha, everything, okay? I don't
know.
You go to
inexpensive hotel, the toilet paper is
very very thin.
You know what I mean?
And you're like,
"What's the message?"
You know, then you know you're a real
lojong person, okay? You don't complain
in the hotel, you know?
Must be some message, you know?
Okay, and that kind of thinking is very
healthy.
That's that's tantric thinking, if you
want Vajrayana.
And you meet people who seem irritating,
they're like, "Get you now, it's a
message." I'm like, "Stop with the
message. I'm I'm tired of all these
messages."
And then and but actually they're right.
Actually it's a good state of mind,
okay?
That's what lojong means, okay? Yiday
choksay. Yiday means whatever happens,
it's a message and be be, you know,
relax.
And think, "Oh, that's okay. That's a
good message. I wonder what I'm supposed
to do in that."
You know, so take everything as a
personal message from Buddha, okay?
Everything. Everything that happens. And
just relax.
Oh, Buddha, I don't know.
Buddha broke the washing machine. I
can't wash my underwear today. Okay,
it's a message.
And relax and enjoy the messages. Okay?
That's real Lojong.
Uh they should do two minutes of Jig Ten
Gön Yönten Chugay.
Uh
This is called Jig Ten Chugay. Say Jig
Ten.
Chugay.
Jig Ten.
Jig Ten means
uh world in a
derogatory sense. The world, you know,
the normal world. Okay?
Everyday world, meaning normal
normal people eat eat poop and die. Eat
poop and die. Eat poopoo and die.
Jig It's called Jig Ten. In Sanskrit,
it's Loka.
The world. Okay? And uh
Jig Ten. Chur means uh
Dharma, right? Chur means Dharma. But
here,
it doesn't mean Dharma. It means
quality.
Gay means eight, number eight. Okay? So,
these are very, very famous list
of eight
bad attitudes.
Okay? And they come from They are You
can find them in the early Lojong
teachings.
The eight verse Lojong.
But they come from earlier, from
Nagarjuna.
And you can find them in I put them here
from Nagarjuna. Uh
Actually, I just I just added it today.
Sorry.
Okay? I'm going to read it to you from
Nagarjuna. Okay? Nagarjuna's version.
Okay? It's found in the letter to a
king.
And Nagarjuna wrote a letter to a king.
Two letters to a king. Okay?
This is from one of those letters.
Uh
Uh here are the eight
worldly attitudes.
Uh and by the way, it starts out with
Jigden Kyab
which means uh
master of the world, and he's referring
to the king, okay? Like
it's kind of an insult.
Get it?
Master of the world. It means you don't
know anything about Dharma.
You're a master of the world. You know
politics, you know economy,
Jigden Kyab.
Nyeida manye. Nye means
you get some money.
Manye means you lose money, okay?
And if you worry too much, if you get
too excited
when you get a lot of money,
that's nye.
And if you get too sad when you lose
your money,
that's manye. Nye and manye, okay? Those
are two that appear. They go together,
okay? And normally it's the same brain.
Uh the kind of brain that's too happy
about money
will also get too sad about losing
money, okay? So they go together. That
kind of thinking goes together.
Oh, I'm so rich. I got so much money,
you know? Then oh, I'm so sad. I'm going
to kill myself. I lost all my money.
They're the same state of mind.
Okay? There's the worldly state of mind
and there's the deeper state of mind,
okay? Worldly state of mind, happy,
so happy when you get some money,
and so sad when you lose money, but
they're the same state of mind. It's the
same It's the same thing.
Uh and we try to not do that. We try to
go nyom. He said go nyom at the
beginning.
Go nyom means uh
flatten it out.
Make it level,
okay? It means don't get too excited
when
you get some money
and don't get so depressed when you lose
some money. Just like, "Hey, you got a
lot of money." Yeah, okay.
I'll donate to Tim.
"Hey, you lost all your money." Yeah,
it's okay. I'll ask Tim for a loan.
It's like, "Okay."
You know, it's okay.
He'll give you, by the way. That's why
he doesn't have money. Okay.
Uh
data midday means uh if
you feel things are very nice, you know,
you're in the Mandarin Oriental Hotel in
Chengdu, um
75th floor.
Oh my god.
They put me there last week.
It's like heaven, you know.
I was thinking to sell my house and move
to the Mandarin Oriental.
Uh
so you're in this luxury uh room day.
I I think it's the best hotel in the
world and I spent many years in hotels,
you know.
Data midday midday By the way, thank you
for
for doing that. We had beautiful classes
in the most beautiful hotel.
Uh
which is appropriate, which is a good
thing.
So, data midday midday means uh
I don't know, everything goes wrong. You
have to sleep at the airport on the
floor.
It happens to everybody, right? Doesn't
matter you're business class.
They cancel the flight, you end up
sleeping. Did you ever do it, Mr. B?
Sleep on the floor in the airport?
That's why you get soft luggage.
Cuz sometimes you have to sleep on it.
Some airport it's dangerous not to sleep
on your luggage.
So, I'm just telling you guys
suggestion.
Uh so, day midday means don't get all
excited if you're in some beautiful
place
and don't get all depressed if you're in
some wealthy place.
Somebody's going to put you in the wind
and wind and oriented tomorrow.
Don't worry about it. Okay, just relax.
Relax. Whatever happens just relax. And
that's wealthy.
Understand? That's rich. The person who
can relax
whatever going on around them,
they are wealthy, super wealthy. Okay,
you know.
They have money, they don't have money,
they have a nice bed, they don't have a
nice bed. But the mind is we call
gonyum. Gonyum means
the flow of the mind is undisturbed.
Uh that's real rich person. That's a
super rich person, okay.
And nobody can take it away from you.
You have it for the rest of your life.
Uh turme means uh
well, nyendan minyam. Nyendan minyam
means
you are famous or nobody heard of you.
Okay, you are very famous or no one
heard of you. Okay, and
don't get all excited.
You know, your last
Instagram
post made 10 million people.
And then the next day all the trolls are
saying bad things about you
online, right? Like some days you wake
up, you're famous for half hour.
And then some days you wake up and
you're a demon for half hour
or 2 hours. And
I just think, "Okay,
you know, that's all right." Don't get
worried about it, okay. Let's say Andy
Warhol said everybody will be famous for
10 minutes
in your life. So, don't get excited.
And as soon as you get famous, you get
you get unfamous. Trust me.
It takes about 10 minutes.
So, don't get all excited, okay? Oh,
everyone says I'm a great teacher.
Then next day, everyone say you're
stupid, you know.
Then a real great teacher is like,
"Oh, I'm a great teacher. Okay."
"Oh, you're stupid." Yeah, okay, I'm
stupid.
And you just feel happy all the time.
That's gonyo. Gonyo means uh
people are excited about you
or people are criticizing you. We had a
We were in the car with Seiji 2 days ago
from the airport in Osaka.
And he's like, "Geshe-la, we just lost a
big, big sponsor, big, big sponsor." I'm
like, "Okay."
You know, and then he We went another
half an hour and he said,
"Looks like the sponsor coming back."
And I'm like, "Okay."
Then when we reached the hotel, he said,
"No, they quit definitely."
Then I'm like,
"Okay."
Then I didn't My mind didn't go like
this, you know. My mind's like, "Okay,
it's all right. We'll we'll
We'll say bye.
We'll say bye. You know, it's okay.
Something else will happen, you know.
You know. So, that's uh nyen daminion.
This is the third set of two, okay? If
you get famous or you don't get famous,
it's like, "Ah,
that's okay."
By the way, it doesn't mean that if
you're doing something naughty,
you shouldn't feel bad. If you're doing
something naughty,
you should feel bad, okay? Uh but if
you're not,
and everyone says you are, then you can
just relax, okay?
All right. Then teme, teme means people
praise you.
"Oh, you're so smart." Or people
tell you you're stupid or something like
that.
And you're just like, "Okay, that's all
right."
I know I'm a genius, you just didn't
figure it out yet.
K9
You know, it's so Trust me, I have been
famous many times and I had many people
criticize me and it doesn't
in the end it it doesn't matter. You are
who you are.
And
be a good person inside
and don't worry what other people say,
okay? Just be famous to yourself.
And that's enough, okay? And then don't
don't think so much about what
Life is extremely short.
Uh if you don't think about
what people say
and you don't think about money
and you don't worry about it you save so
much time.
You know, then your mind is available to
to read the great books or something
like that. You know, then you have time
to
to read John Brady's whole database.
If If you're not worrying about other
people, what they say about you just
just let it go. You don't have room in
your mind, okay? You don't have room to
get very happy that people are you're
getting famous
and think about it all the time or
someone criticize you and you think
about it all the time
that time you cannot use to learn more
wisdom.
That that time you cannot learn more
wisdom. Your mind is booked.
Your your thought time is booked.
And I've worked very hard my whole life
to to take that time back.
You know, people say, "Oh, you're so
wonderful." I'm like, "Yeah, okay.
Let's read something." And then people
say, "You're really stupid." I'm like,
"Yeah, okay."
And uh
you know, I just
don't worry about it and focus on
wisdom. Focus on improving yourself.
And and then the it's it's your whole
life is fun. My whole day is fun. The
whole day is fun. I mean, 99%
of my life is really fun.
Yeah, I'm just having fun all the time.
I don't care if things are going well or
if things aren't going well.
I'm just having fun, okay? And that's
mojo. That's mojo. Mhm.
All right. Mhm.
I was supposed to give you a chance to
get rich.
So, you'll be happy.
Right?
So, Tim.
Any
Ivan, I'm going to call him I I Ivan.
Ivan.
Mhm.
You're supposed to look at pictures.
Rob, who's got the money, honey?
You got the money? I'm paying this one.
I think I have enough.
Yeah.
Anytime I get some money, I have to get
rid of it quickly.
We were going to have item contest
today, right?
We're supposed to guess. Tim, do you
want to come? Or Tim, you want to sit up
here and
help me?
Giving away money is fun.
He's throwing it around like that.
Yeah.
There's one two people I can't stand.
One is in Taiwan, Mark Wu.
And one is in Arizona called Word Smith.
They take all my money.
Always answer the correct answer.
I met Word has a new baby.
And uh he also inherited two girls. So,
he has three girls. Plus, he has his
wife, who's four girls.
And uh
I don't know.
I feel like I'm paying for college
scholarships.
You ready?
You got pictures for me? Who's going to
show the pictures?
Uh I'll give you pictures, hang on.
I'll give you. Yeah.
Uh
Raise your hand. Tim's going to
Oh, wait. $100 a $100 a picture, okay?
Do you know any of the the custom uh
If you give the wrong answer, you have
to pay us $100.
Just kidding.
Okay.
Ready for the death.
Uh let me see if that's what it is. Do
you remember, Tim?
Uh yeah, but I'm just Oh, it's in the
canteen.
Yeah, that's pretty good. Yeah, $100.
Yeah, thank you.
Either Either take refuge in the three
jewels as you die
or uh
What is today? The try to remember your
Dharma as you die.
Okay.
And by the way,
it's the worst moment in your life. I
guarantee you. It's the worst moment in
your life.
And it's very hard to remember your
training.
And uh
And we have to practice, okay?
My My teacher said practice when you
fall asleep.
Every night, practice dying a little bit
every night.
And can you make a prayer for all people
while you fall asleep?
Then when you fall to the big sleep,
uh
it comes automatically. That's the real
meaning of picture, $100. Yay, okay,
next one.
Oh.
Center is center.
Mr. Bean translate?
Yes, Mr. Bean.
Uh your karma will bring you to the
Buddha paradise.
Yeah, instead of what?
Uh instead of bringing you to the lower
realms.
Yay! How do you
It means uh
if you pray to
to go to the lower realms to help people
after you die.
If you pray to go to the lower realms to
help people,
it will take you up.
That prayer will take you up.
You will end up on a beach with the most
beautiful being in the universe.
You understand?
Okay.
Okay. Next.
Oh, thank you.
Uh thank you, Geshe la. Uh
She took notes. It's very
good idea. Very financial good idea.
Geshe la will translate. Um so um Rico
says uh there's someone who is jumping
into the river, try to rescue the other
person, and the action of doing that uh
like um there's a rainbow strike on her
or him directly that send her to the
heaven directly.
No. Okay, good.
Uh
Actually, the boat the boat was too
heavy and the boat is sinking and they
they jumped off to to save the other
people to help the other people. Okay,
good. Um next one.
This is a little bit
Don't just think about the fart fart uh
sound because that's just a natural and
when you do do yoga, you will burp, you
will fart, and that's all natural.
Okay, not bad.
Yeah.
I'm not saying I'd give $100 for every
fart. I'm not saying that.
Uh
but what was the context?
The context is um when we die, some
people think we could just by saying
fart fart and what kind of secret or
weird sound and then we could go to
Okay, good. I got it done.
go to
Yeah.
It means uh when you die,
uh your body will make some strange
noises.
And don't don't It's not special. It's
just prana. Just prana going here there.
It's like you ate beans or something.
It's not a
big thing, okay?
The real
the real thing is in your mind. Do you
Do you die with love or not?
It's not some magic thing or magic or
fate or something like that. Okay.
It's love. Go with love.
Next picture.
Okay, this is a
Okay, this is a lock. This means to
to shut the door towards the lower
realms or lower or lower rebirths.
The cure is to have the understanding of
the pen story when you're dying or most
importantly more important than like the
tantric practices of Mahamudra and stuff
like that is to have Bodhicitta at the
moment of the death.
Okay. Dodo, I have to tell you
something.
Yes.
Your name has two parts, Dodo.
Sometimes person give a $200 answer to
the $100 question.
So
Really? OH, YES.
THANK YOU.
GETTING RICH.
Thank you.
Dodo.
Don't get too happy.
Next picture.
Try this.
Mhm.
Um Uh
Uh
Can I ask you?
Yeah, it's about
all the rivers were running to the same
ocean and all the person at the end were
going to the Buddha paradise, going to
the same direction.
Yeah.
The dividing line
between normal death and special death
is
you think about other people after
death.
Can I help other people?
So, I think it's $100. I thank you I'll
give you $100 for taking good notes.
Thank you. Thank you, teacher.
Thank you.
NOT TO ME. OKAY.
ALL RIGHT, we got one more.
If you are real Buddhist, then you're
always in a good mood and always
smiling.
I did that.
Yeah, and they said at the same time
they said there's miracles. You can do
miracles. You can
walk on the water. You can walk through
the stone.
You can fly in the sky.
But, even rats do that. Even birds do
that. Even fish do that.
It's to have the love for other people.
That's the real miracle.
All right.
I want to go to the peaches. Let's go to
the peaches.
What's it mean?
I I don't remember my side.
It means
that you want to look good to yourself.
You want to impress yourself.
So, you keep the main one of the two
judges.
So, you're not
Mhm, contradictory.
Okay, you judge yourself. You don't
depend on other people to judge.
Yeah.
And then, what about the
What's that thing about mangoes?
What's that thing about
Good good, bad bad, good bad,
bad good. And it's hard to tell, so you
have to
um approach the same.
Yeah. Yeah. Good. $100.
Last one's too easy. I cancel that.
All right.
All right. Thank you.
Next time we'll do online. Uh we we have
to set it up, okay? How to get the money
online.
Okay.
Sophie Chow, you remember I was in
Okura Hotel
and one gentleman came up to me. He
said,
"Hey, you owe me $500." I'm like,
"What?"
He said, "You came to Tokyo 3 years ago
and and you made a bet with me and I won
the money and you never paid me." I'm
like,
"Hey, you have to collect the money
yourself, okay?"
Okay.
Uh it was very funny though. I gave him
the money though. Okay.
All right. Uh going on number two. So,
we had the eight worldly attitudes
and then uh
we're at yang. First word is yang, you
guys.
We text people.
Y E N G, okay? Yang kang tub na jom ba
yin.
Young means uh you got distracted, okay?
Uh jong means what?
Jong, lojong. Yeah, clean or you got
used to it, okay?
And uh took na means if you can do it.
It means
uh
if you can
keep this practice even when you're
distracted by something else, then you
really have real lojong. Okay? And he
gives example. Shebney thought selchar
mepata.
If you're not too good at riding a
horse, sem my young na temikur.
If you're focused on the horse and the
horse bucks,
you won't fall off.
Uh but sem my uh young young na kur.
Uh if you if you look at something else
and suddenly the horse bucks, you will
fall off. If you're not a very
experienced rider, what's the point?
Yeah, if your lojong is good, if you do
it all the time,
every time someone gives you money,
you're like, "Yeah, okay."
And every time you lose money, you're
like, "Yeah, okay."
Then maybe we should say yeah, okay, and
not lojong.
It's like yeah, okay. No, I got yeah,
okay.
Okay? So,
how do you know that you're good at
lojong?
You It means when you're tired or you're
busy,
uh still you can keep it. Yeah, okay.
Okay? When you're tired or many things
going on, very busy,
uh
and you lose some money, you're like,
"Yeah, okay."
Or you get some money, you're like,
"Yeah, okay." You don't fall off your
lojong horse.
Okay? It's natural, totally natural.
There's some people like that.
I come from Arizona. I grew up in
Arizona. Supposed to be we are all
cowboys. I have cowboy shirt.
Uh
and uh when I went to Princeton, uh a
very good-looking girl
said, "You from Arizona?" And yeah, "You
can ride horse." "Oh, yeah."
"You want to go horse riding with me?"
I'm like, "Yeah."
Actually, I never I rode a horse once or
something.
And uh
it was like a old tired horse.
So, she got these two very strong horses
and
we went for a ride and my horse start to
run, you know.
And he's running and and I'm like,
"Stop! Stop!" And then he's like, "Okay,
stop." Then I went
I fall down and she said she said, "You
sure you know how to ride a horse?" I'm
like, "Actually, I never ride a horse,
you know."
Then she didn't want to go on a date
with me. Anyway,
uh
but some people so natural on a horse.
The horse does everything and it's just
natural. Okay.
Their lojong horse is natural. Their
connection to their lojong is natural.
They never get kicked off. Okay. Yeah,
okay.
Yeah, okay.
Lojong kunga majong mani
uh lojong kunga majong mani datse meday
tashi nambashi.
Uh if a person who tried to study
lojong, but they didn't lojong.
Then that's a person who doesn't know
how to ride a horse.
Uh sem nyembe gakshe shigye sem nyen
mema. What's the wild horse in this
example?
Is if somebody says something bad to
you. Okay. You're stupid or you look
terrible or you know,
"Didn't your mom teach you to brush your
teeth?"
or something, you know.
And then you're like,
"What?"
You know. And that means the horse
jumps. And then do you fall off or not?
Or do you like you start to fall off and
you like whoa wait wait wait wait wait.
I'm low jump person. I'm low jump
person.
You know. When it becomes natural.
Small you know they say your flight
canceled.
I I had a fun
plane ride with Stahli recently.
You know. They're like
I got used to business class cuz I can
sleep. And I can work. And and I pay the
extra we pay the extra money. I go
business class.
I I translated many books in business
class.
The guy always told The guy told me on
this plane. He said you're amazing. You
know you work the whole time and then
you sleep anytime.
That's amazing. Then s-
We got on the plane and they said um
you have to sit in the in the tourist
class. I'm like what?
And they're like you know we don't have
business class seat today. You got
canceled. Your business class canceled.
I'm like
Okay.
And I got a Did you remember this guy?
He sat between us. He's kind of fat.
He's like
I'm trying to type like this you know.
And I get the computer ready and I put
it on my knees and and he's like
And I'm like this. I had an experience
for 19 years in New York so I can do.
And I'm like this. And I'm like okay.
All right.
Then the stewardess came back. This is a
couple weeks ago.
In Peru. When we came back from Peru.
Then the stewardess came Are you Mr.
Rhodes? Yes.
Oh. You are global service. Global
service is a secret
business class in United Airlines.
And uh
you cannot apply.
Uh the board of directors votes
secretly. And they and they write you a
letter and they say you are global
service. And then, they treat you just
like a llama.
And that's the only place I get treated
Uh
is there like, "Oh, Mr. Rose, it's so
good to see you, you know.
Do you need anything?" You know,
I'm like, "I want a coffee." Okay, yes,
sir.
So, she said,
"We got a business class for you." And
then,
you're just like, "Yeah, okay."
Okay, I lost a business class at 3:00.
Okay, then 3:10 I got the business
class. I'm like,
"Okay, actually I was a little more."
Okay.
Okay, so I just to stay even, okay?
Uh
lojong benny
us hang on. That's how maybe that's a
man.
So, the sign of a person whose lojong is
not perfect yet is
uh when the person insults them.
Uh they they go,
"I'm not stupid you."
Lojong lojong lojong lojong, then you're
like,
"Okay."
"It's all right." But, you you don't
remember right away. That means you
don't have lojong yet, okay? Got it?
So, it's like, "You're stupid." And then
you go, "You."
Lojong lojong lojong, then you're like,
"Okay."
"Yeah, I'm stupid. It's okay.
Okay, all right." That means you almost
fell off the horse. Got it?
Yeah, and you're not expert yet. So, the
lojong real lojong person, "You're
stupid." Yeah, okay.
No delay.
No time delay.
"You're stupid." Yeah, mhm.
"Yeah, okay."
"You're so handsome." Yeah, okay.
Okay, all right. Chance in line.
Contour shido shido in, okay? If you
uh similar control sheet
going to jump on to occasion chin and
timber similar control Shindoryin sheet.
You can You can delay your anger. Lord
Jong Ben Ni Sam Young Ben Nang
a person who's good at Lord Jong even if
they get distracted by something else,
you know, like uh
there's something going on, I don't
know. The plane is like this, right?
And but your Lord Jong is very strong.
And And then it doesn't matter. It
doesn't affect you, okay.
Chom Esha Ngid Dek Tok. Even other
people can hit you.
Uh
or say They can even hit you, and you're
like, "Yeah, okay."
Boom. "Yeah, okay." What did Jesus say?
He said some cool stuff.
Someone hit you on this side
say, "Hey,
you want to use the other side?"
You know, that's real Lord Jong, right?
Somebody hit you, and you're like
And
you like, "Do you want to do
If they steal your sweater If they steal
your coat
uh remember to ask them if they need
your sweater also.
That's so much Lord Jong. Really good
Lord Jong. Okay, control me you want to
Lord Jong Ben say
$100 say
That's the Lord Jong say.
$100.
Close. Is that Gibson?
Sema. Say. Say.
Yeah, good. $100.
That's it.
Handsome guy from
Taichung.
Taichung Feijang Bang.
Taichung the Feijang Bang the Ren.
Okay. All right.
Okay.
Do I have to this Q&A now, Tim?
Yes, Tim.
Huh?
Is it time?
But what what's the plan?
Okay, let's do I'm I'm going to make a
mark where we finished at the horse.
Okay, and that that say
that say was you have low tone
if someone hit you and you're like,
"Yeah, okay."
Okay, hitting is harder than calling you
stupid, right?
I mean
most people
if a lot of people can stay patient if
someone call you stupid.
But when they're physical, something
physical
uh almost everybody gets angry, okay? Uh
even on the subway or something.
Okay.
All right, questions.
No question.
Uh thank you, Geshe-la.
Thank you for coming. It's good to see
you after so many years.
Yeah, yeah. I'm very
uh exciting and very touched. My
question is that uh
I remember you said that uh 100
meditation items is very important uh
very important. Um it's lucky that I
went through all these uh lamrim causes
uh one by one and taught by you.
And then um I put it all into the
words. Um
oh the the
call that uh three principal path.
Mm, nice.
And then the the lower capacity
Yeah.
middle capacity
and the higher capacity.
Yeah.
Okay? And now um my question is that uh
because you you taught us to
uh
once we need to complete all these 100
items meditation before we can get the
secret teaching. So, my question is that
what's the standard? What's the standard
to for example
uh
lower capacity and
the lower capacity
items and what's the standard to pass
one item meditation? What's the
standard?
Okay, good. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Thank you.
Uh
in the very beginning of this book they
discuss different ways to teach it.
And one is called the
There's many kinds of tea. Tea means uh
style to teach it.
And one is called Nyamti. Nyamti means
uh
There's a way to teach Lojong.
There's a way to teach this book that
you learn it in a retreat. You learn in
retreat.
And each time they come to a
new idea
you stop the class and everyone goes to
their retreat cabin and they they
meditate. You
And until they reach the inner
until they for example until they reach
Lojong
they don't come back to the class.
You know?
I think I suspect
that the Lama when the student come back
to the class they say
Then if the student go
then they say, "Oh, you don't have
Lojong. You you go back.
Go back.
Go back again. Try some more.
You know? So, there's a way to teach
this
book
called Nyamti. If it took us 13 years to
reach this
without Nyangti, I think it will take us
130 years
to teach it with a Nyangti. So, I didn't
do it that way.
Uh but I would say that the in the
Lojong, in the Lamrim, generally in
Lamrim, if your motivation is to stay
out of the lower realms, animal hell,
preta,
then that's
beginner
motivation, okay?
And then uh second level motivation,
medium motivation is that I don't want
to
come back to this
life at all. I don't want to come back
to suffering life, any kind of suffering
life. I don't want to come back to the
wheel of life. That's called medium
motivation.
And then I would like to help all people
to escape this life, suffering life.
That's called bodhicitta or highest
motivation. So, in in general,
those are the classical
three levels in the Lamrim, but in the
Lojong,
uh it's a little bit different. It's how
natural
is your reaction. How good are you on
the horse? Is the Lojong reaction
automatic or not?
Uh then that determines whether you're
what's your level, okay? How how how
much
how natural, how automatic is your
reaction to someone hurting you?
You know, how long does it take you to
remember you're a Buddhist?
Sometimes it takes 2 weeks, you know?
You're like, "God damn, god damn." And
then you know, "Wait, I'm a Buddhist,
you know?
I'm not supposed to think like that, you
know?
It's stuff."
That's in the Lojong, that's
time, judged by time. How long does it
take you to remember you're a Buddhist?
That's good. Uh
what Tony's referring to is uh
I said if you finish uh can study the
100 of those pictures,
then I will teach uh
Diamond Way, okay?
So, we'll see.
I'm still checking.
But, you're close.
In the meantime, there are many great uh
Diamond Way teachers, uh John Brady, uh
Venerable Ellie. They're
They're doing a good job, Connie.
They're They're doing beautiful Diamond
Way teaching, Kelsang
Sonam taught some.
Yeah.
There's lots of people teaching, okay?
Connect with somebody
who fits you.
You know the famous story of my wife.
We went to buy jeans for her.
Anyone tell her I told this story, I
will kill you.
Okay?
I won't be a large young person at that
time.
Uh
so, we went to the store to buy pants.
And
those ladies store are very cruel, T.
Why?
There's no place for the guy to sit
down. You have to stand up. It's a
floor, there's no chairs.
You know, you have to stand up while the
lady tries on 20 kinds of this thing.
So, anyway, she tried 41 or 42 pairs of
pants. Guess how many she bought?
Yeah, zero.
Yeah, so
your Diamond Way teacher should fit you
like a good pair of pants.
Okay? And then you should take your
time.
Try 42 teachers.
See which one fit you, okay? And And
Geshe Michael doesn't fit everybody, you
know? Some people say, "Oh, he's crazy."
Or he's too funny or he's not
funny enough or
not enough hair or something.
Then uh
find the one who fit you. You don't have
to take me, you know. It can be
find the person who fits you.
And that's the best. Okay, that's best
for everybody. It's really uncomfortable
to wear the pant which is too small.
Right?
Okay.
All right.
Nick Lashaw is coming tomorrow. I'm so
excited. Uh
yeah.
He He He went to Portugal or something.
He said, "Gashaw,
there's a special demon
in Portugal, you know." I'm like, "What?
Demon?" He said, "Yeah, the special
demon."
I'm like, "Whoa, what's a demon?"
He said, "Uh they At night, when you
sleep,
they go into your
closet
and they sew your pants smaller.
Then next day you try the pants and
especially after COVID, they got smaller
and smaller. He said, "That demon is
following me."
And
yeah, I think he he came to my house.
Okay, other question?
3 minute, maybe one more.
Thank you.
Uh
I would call you sensei. Can I call you
You can call me anything except well.
And so, in Japan, I live in Japan, so we
say sensei for a teacher.
Cool.
Thank you very much for your teaching.
Uh I have a question. How would you
comfort uh someone uh who um whose
relative died as act of terror or war.
Because recently the world is, for me I
feel like the world is getting a place
where war is going to be more and more
common thing.
And, uh, maybe in Japan people still
don't feel,
um, related to what is going on in other
parts of the world, but because I was
born in Ukraine and then I moved to
Israel. And
now I feel it very, very close to me and
I want to go back to Israel and,
Ukraine and I want to help people to
kind of live in the place where people
were cruelly murdered.
Um, and I, yeah, I'm curious how to, to
even talk with people who went through
so much.
Yeah, good, good question. We used to
have all of our programs in Irpin,
outside of Kyiv.
And it's a beautiful, small city like,
uh, near, very similar to Flagstaff.
And, uh,
that was attacked badly and many, many
families, children,
women were killed there.
And there's video, you can watch it and
it's very, very terrible.
So, how can you
what should you do? And, um, we had the
good luck to, uh,
uh, the, Vika, Victoria and Vitaly,
where are you? They helped us, uh,
a lot and we my wife and I wanted to and
John Brady
and Connie, we wanted to invite some
Ukrainians to come and
come and live in our place and we take
care of them.
So, uh, the Tatangos helped us a lot.
And,
uh, it's interesting to me they did not
choose themselves.
They choose other people and uh,
So, we invited some people We invited
two two families to come. So far, only
the wife can come
because the husband and the son had to
fight.
So,
you know, they came and we we have two
beautiful ladies from Ukraine.
Uh Tatiana and Iryna and uh
We are
You know, me and my wife and all my
friends, all the Rim Rim are
special Rim Rim people.
We talk about it, you know, like how can
we take care of them?
And obviously, we have to buy things for
them. You know, we got them a real I
I looked Well, Rob helped me. We looked
at many apartments in Rim Rim.
And we chose the best one.
And then we found out it's Scott's old
apartment.
He bought bought it. And he
We're like, "Wait, this is Scott's
apartment."
Uh Scott Bessette's apartment. So, we we
rented it and it's very beautiful.
And uh we put them there and then uh we
have a friend who bought a a new car for
them.
It's a new Toyota uh RAV4. It's
beautiful beautiful car.
And uh they can't drive.
I mean, they don't have a license. Iryna
can drive. Uh Tatiana didn't have much
experience.
Uh
but they got their license.
Uh finally, she Iryna got hers.
Tatiana's still working on it and um
So, they have a beautiful new car. They
have a beautiful garage and uh we got
them some work and they they make juices
for the cafe.
And they make good money. They make they
make pretty good money.
Yeah, we overpaid them and uh
Then my wife and I were always
talking about them, you know, like how
can we help them?
And cuz we noticed they're still
traumatized.
You know, they have beautiful car, they
have all the American dream,
you know, beautiful apartment, beautiful
car,
like everything. Rob
and Rosa
made them a beautiful apartment and
but they're still traumatized, you know,
and they still get depression and they
still have a lot of
emotional problems and I asked my wife,
you know,
"What kind of Dharma should I teach
them, you know?" And she's like,
"Maybe we should just hug them."
And I'm like, "What?" And they said,
"Irina's birthday was yesterday."
Uh
sorry, Tatiana, Tanya. And uh
And it was her birthday yesterday and
and my wife is like, "The most important
thing
Geshe Lama, she calls me mine,
but sometimes when she wants to be
sarcastic, she says, "Geshe Lama."
She says uh
"Maybe they don't need philosophy right
now.
Maybe they need a lot of hugs
and a birthday cake and treat them with
sweet sweet beha- We made dinner for
them. She and I made dinner for them.
They came with two Russian friends, uh
Olga and
what's the other one?
Uh anyway, two Russians, two Ukrainians.
They came and we made the Christmas tree
together. It took like 3 hours
and it was really fun and uh
and I think uh
so what my teacher said,
uh
sometimes it's not philosophy what
people need. Sometimes they need a hug.
Sometimes they need a birthday cake, you
know.
Sometimes they need a Christmas tree.
And I think as a Buddhist, you have to
be sensitive to that, You know, I think
for the trauma
of people in Ukraine and Israel or
Palestine, that these
people need hugs, you know,
and they need a lot of attention.
And they need personal attention in
make
you know, a lot of touch touch and
encouragement. And I think
I think that's better Dharma.
When a person is traumatized, I I don't
think talking to people about
philosophy is is
it's not the right time. In my life,
a long life, I think it's not the right
time. I think this is the time that
people need a hug.
And they need they need us to spend time
with them.
And they need to be quiet with us and uh
have some fun together and things like
that. Yester- For her birthday
yesterday, she went to uh
flamenco performance in New York.
That was She was really happy. So, I
think uh
my deep philosophy answer is hugs hugs.
Uh in the for the first year
or 18 months, something like that.
Thank you.
Okay.